Guide to the Todd Webb photographs, 1948-1979, bulk 1948-1951 RL.11701
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Todd Webb photographs
1948-1979
1948-1951
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11701
1 Linear Feet 1 box 25 prints
Collection consists of 25 gelatin silver prints of images taken in France by noted American photographer Todd Webb. The majority were taken from 1948 to 1951, with some from the 1970s, on the streets of Paris, particularly in the Latin Quarter, with other images from small towns and rural areas in Provence and one from Le Cannet, on the French Riviera. Subjects include streets, storefronts, squares, restaurants, outdoor advertising, doorways, and other city scenes, some with pedestrians and other figures. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arrangement
Arranged in chronological order according to image date marked on print verso.
Biographical / Historical
Todd Webb was a noted American photographer based in New York City and later, in Maine, where he passed away in 2000. Born in Detroit in 1905 as Charles Clayton Webb III, he spent his young adult years working in various jobs around the country, then turned to photography in the 1940s, studying and forming friendships with major photographers and artists such as Ansel Adams, Alfred Steiglitz, Georgia O'Keefe, Beaumont Newhall, and Roy Stryker. He moved to Paris in 1949, where he met his wife, and stayed there for the next four years, after which he returned to the U.S. to stay. Webb's photographs of New York and Paris are among his most well-known bodies of work, and his prints are found in the collections of major American art institutions.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use requires the photographer's permission.
Provenance
The Todd Webb photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from the Howard Greenberg Gallery in 2018.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The 25 gelatin silver prints are titled, copyright stamped, signed, and dated by the photographer. Almost all bear a copyright date of 1976, likely the date of printing. Original identifiers are also marked on each print. Other markings include the Howard Greenberg Gallery's identifiers.
Content Description
Collection consists of 25 gelatin silver prints of images taken in France by noted American photographer Todd Webb. The majority were taken from 1948 to 1951, with some from the 1970s, on the streets of Paris, particularly in the Latin Quarter, with other images from small towns and rural areas in Provence and one from Le Cannet, on the French Riviera. Subjects include streets, storefronts, squares, restaurants, doorways, outdoor advertising, and other city scenes, some with pedestrians and other figures. Paper sizes are 8.5 x 11 and 11x14 inches. Image dimensions are noted for each print entry. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Architecture -- France -- Photographs; Documentary photographers -- United States; Documentary photography -- France; Street photography -- France -- Paris; Street photography -- France -- Provence; France -- Photographs; Le Cannet (France) -- Photographs; Paris (France) -- Photographs; Paris (France) -- Social life and customs; Provence (France) -- Photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Gelatin silver prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Webb, Todd
- Paris, Provence, and Le Cannet, 1948-1979; 25 prints 8.5x11, 11x14 inches
  Scope and Contents
  Prints arranged in order by year, and within dates, by title.
  Copyright statements, dates, original identifiers, and titles all were transcribed from information on the prints written in the photographer's hand.
  There are two paper sizes: 11x14 and 8.5x11. Dimensions given indicate the image size.
  - 4th Republic Restaurant, Rue Jacob, Paris, 1948; Image size: 12 1/2 x 9 1/2 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11701-P-0001)
    Original identifier: 45FR48-36
    Copyright stamp: 1976
  - 4th Republic Restaurant, Rue Jacob, Paris, 1948; Image size: 12 3/8 x 9 1/2 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11701-P-0002)
  - Place du Tertre, Montmartre, 1948; Image size: 12 3/8 x 9 1/2 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11701-P-0003)
    Original identifier: 57FR48-16
    View of Restaurant á la Mère Catherine.
  - Cour Mirabeau, Aix-En-Provence, 1949; Image size: 12 3/8 x 9 1/2 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11701-P-0004)
    Original identifier: 44FR49-8
    Copyright stamp: 1976; printed 1978
  - Left Bank hotel, Paris, 1949; Image size: 9 x 7 3/8 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11701-P-0005)
    Original identifier: 810FR49-253
    Copyright stamp: 1976, "Vintage"
    A view of the courtyard, Hôtel d'Aubusson.
  - Place de la Contrascarpe, Paris, 1949; Image size: 12 3/8 x 9 3/8 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11701-P-0006)
    Original identifier: 44FR49-69
  - Rue de Coulmiers near Square de Chatillon, Paris, 1949; Image size: 7 1/2 x 9 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11701-P-0007)
    Original identifier: 810FR45-205
  - 16th century door, Ile St. Louis, Paris, 1950; Image size: 9 x 7 1/2 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11701-P-0008)
    Original identifier: 810FR50-86
    Copyright stamp: 1976, "Vintage print"
  - Paris, 1950; Image size: 9 x 7 1/2 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11701-P-0009)
    Original identifier: 810FR50-272
  - Paris, 1950; Image size: 9 x 7 1/2 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11701-P-0010)
    Original identifier: 810FR50-209
    Outdoor wall advertising for Dubonnet, and below, smaller broadsides for movie cinemas.
  - Passage du Moulin Vert, Paris, 1950; Image size: 9 x 7 1/2 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11701-P-0011)
    Original identifier: 810FR50-85
  - Passage du Moulin Vert, Paris, 1950; Image size: 9 x 7 1/2 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11701-P-0012)
    Original identifier: 810FR50-202
  - Place de la Contrascarpe, Paris, 1950; 7 1/2 x 9 1/4 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11701-P-0013)
    Original identifier: 810FR50-297
    Seen in the image is the façade of the café, "Au Nègre joyeux."
  - Place St. Sulpice, Paris, 1950; 12 3/8 x 9 3/8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11701-P-0014)
    Original identifier: 45FR50-229
  - Rue Alésia, Paris, 1950; Image size: 9 1/4 x 7 3/8 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11701-P-0015)
    Original identifier: 810FR50-247
    Features the restaurant "Au Bon Coin"
  - Rue des Plantes, Paris, 1950; Image size: 9 x 7 3/8 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11701-P-0016)
    Original identifier: 810FR50-282
  - Tooth paste ad, Paris, 1950; 12 x 9 1/4 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11701-P-0017)
    Original identifier: 45FR50-2A
    Copyright stamp: 1976, "4/25"
    Outdoor advertising on buildings in a street; includes a giant man's head advertising toothpaste, and political campaign posters.
  - Early Spring, Avenue du Maine, Paris, 1951; 9 1/2 x 12 1/2 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11701-P-0018)
    Original identifier: 45FR51-45
  - Rue des Plantes, Paris, 1951; Image size: 9 1/4 x 7 3/4 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11701-P-0019)
    Original identifier: 810FR51-292
  - Road near St. Cecile, Provence, 1971; 12 1/4 x 9 3/8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11701-P-0020)
    Original identifier: 44FR71-89
  - Woman sewing, Bollene, Provence, 1971; 12 1/4 x 9 3/8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11701-P-0021)
    Original identifier: 44FR71-13
  - Elegant door, Arles, Provence, 1972; 12 1/4 x 9 3/8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11701-P-0022)
    Original identifier: 44FR72-8
  - Mathematician's house, Le Cannet, France, 1972; 12 1/4 x 9 3/8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11701-P-0023)
    Original identifier: 44FR72-39
    Business sign on building: "Géomètre-expert," a professional surveyor.
  - Ville Neuve d'Avignon, Provence, 1972; 12 1/4 x 9 3/8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11701-P-0024)
    Original identifier: 44FR72-62
  - Hôtel de Ville, Paris, 1979 May; 11 7/8 x 10 1/2 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11701-P-0025)
    Original identifier: 44FR79-22
    Copyright stamp: 1979, "Vintage"